<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>socialism on mbg</title>
    <link>https://blog.gum.pt/tags/socialism/</link>
    <description>mbg (socialism)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 18:58:45 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://blog.gum.pt/tags/socialism/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Graeber&#39;s Oeuvre</title>
      <link>https://blog.gum.pt/notes/graeber/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 18:58:45 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://blog.gum.pt/notes/graeber/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If I could write like anyone, I would write like David Graeber.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say that based on how the first writing of his in &lt;em&gt;The Baffler&lt;/em&gt; I came
across&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; wormed its way into my brain, a reference whenever I had to spend too
much of my day doing &amp;ldquo;busywork,&amp;rdquo; figuring out why the tickets in the bug tracker
had a cyclical reference making the root of the cause undecipherable, filling
out status updates in three separate but Very Important places, listening to
friends describe what ran them out of academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say that based on his political analysis, having referenced his &lt;a href=&#34;https://nymag.com/nymetro/realestate/neighborhoods/features/14884/&#34;&gt;analysis of
British elections
post-Brexit&lt;/a&gt;
more often than anything else when trying to describe fundamental political
problems in the United States to anyone else, or predict (somewhat accurately)
what would happen in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say that because he had a knack for calling out bullshit and naming it such,
going semi-viral for calling the current state of work an epidemic of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strike.coop/bullshit-jobs/&#34;&gt;Bullshit
Jobs&lt;/a&gt;, later expanding the thesis into a
book, writing so many sentences that made me want to yell and scream and stamp
my feet that someone finally knows what they&amp;rsquo;re talking about, has their finger
on the pulse but the larger picture in mind, an acute and terminal understanding
of the world around us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer clearly isn&amp;rsquo;t economic: it&amp;rsquo;s moral and political. The ruling
class has figured out that a happy and productive population with free time
on their hands is a mortal danger (think of what started to happen when this
even began to be approximated in the &amp;rsquo;60s). And, on the other hand, the
feeling that work is a moral value in itself, and that anyone not willing to
submit themselves to some kind of intense work discipline for most of their
waking hours deserves nothing, is extraordinarily convenient for them.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say that because his humor comes through despite this subject matter, how
bureaucratic structures in our government are reflected in our languages and
thoughts, how The Left was fighting (and losing!) the wrong battles, how there
would never be The Revolution, the one moment where you could point to a Before
and an After, clearly demarcated by drastic improvements in people&amp;rsquo;s lives, but
that we need to work every single day to try to make the world around us what it
needs to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone once figured out that the average American will spend a cumulative six
months of life waiting for traffic lights to change. I don’t know if similar
figures are available for how long it takes to fill out forms, but it must be
at least as long. No population in the history of the world has spent nearly
so much time engaged in paperwork.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of his books, articles, blog posts, interviews, tweets, coughs and other
gutteral utterances, are worth reading closely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A footnote is required to note how wonderful the title is: &lt;a href=&#34;https://thebaffler.com/salvos/of-flying-cars-and-the-declining-rate-of-profit&#34;&gt;Of Flying Cars and the Declining Rate of Profit.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.strike.coop/bullshit-jobs/&#34;&gt;https://www.strike.coop/bullshit-jobs/&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>